A Guide to the WRVA Radio Collection, 1925-2000
Library of Virginia
- Series XI: Sound Recordings, 1929-1995, 630 compact discs. Duration: 317 hr., 40 min., 38 sec.
  - Inauguration of Davis Young Paschall as the Twenty-third President of the College of William and Mary in Virginia, 13 October 1961, (WRVA - 229); 1 compact disc. Duration: 45 min., 49 sec.
    Recording of the inauguration of Dr. Davis Young Paschall (1911-2001) as the 23rd President of the College of William and Mary, on 13 October 1961. Includes introduction by James M. Robertson, rector of the Board of Visitors, the taking of the oath by Paschall, remarks by State Superintendent of Instruction Woodrow W. Wilkerson (1913-1986) and U.S. Senator A. Willis Robertson (1887-1971), as well as the inaugural address by Paschall.
  - Jack Clements European Tour, 10 July 1958, (WRVA - 446-448); 3 compact discs. Duration: 2 hr., 7 min., 4 sec.
    These are recordings of Jack Clements' broadcasts back to the WRVA studios while participating in an Air Force press tour in the spring of 1958. Clements joined reporters from all over the country as guests of the United States Air Force on tours of Bermuda, the Azores, England, France and Germany, usually visiting air bases. Clements reports on the people, landscape and culture of each place. As this is an Air Force sponsored tour, much of the focus is on the reactions of local citizens to the presence of the American military in their country, or the feelings of Americans living abroad. While in Europe, the interviews address the defense of the various countries against attacks of Soviet aggression, the business of NATO and rebuilding efforts following World War II.
  - Jack Clements News, 9 September 1958, (WRVA - 449); 1 compact disc. Duration: 16 min., 12 sec.
    This is a recording of a broadcast of the 8 a.m. news, featuring Jack Clements. The topics include the wait in Charlottesville for a federal judge's decision on the legality of the Charlottesville school officials' refusal to accept applications from thirty black pupils to attend white public schools. Other school integration news includes the judge's decisions on the Warren County situation in regard to desegregation, as well as the situations in Alexandria, Newport News and the city of Richmond. The broadcast also features a report by Clements and Harry Monroe on the Richmond city council's activities and other local news.
  - James River Call, 30 December 1950, (WRVA - 166); 1 compact disc. Duration: 15 min., 3 sec.
    Features various choral and orchestral selections, including "Now Thank We All Our God" by The World Choristers, "My Pretty Girl" by Russ Morgan's Orchestra, and "It Was Nice While it Lasted" by the Eddie Howard Orchestra. The host of the show also reads numerous commercial spots for the Willard Tablet Company.
  - James River Flood: VAB Community Service Award, AP Continuing Story, November 1985, (WRVA - 581); 1 compact disc. Duration: 19 min., 45 sec.
    Contains sound clips of WRVA news broadcasts covering the flooding of the James River in November 1985.
  - Janssen, Mary Patton, Interview, 6 June 1956, (WRVA - 81); 1 compact disc. Duration: 6 min., 20 sec.
    Telephone interview, 6 June 1956, with Mary Patton Janssen, while she was in London competing in the British Women's Amateur Open, conducted by Jack Clements.
  - Jefferson Davis Memorial, [25 June 1952], (WRVA - 303); 1 compact disc. Duration: 42 min., 5 sec.
    This is a recording of the ceremonies marking the unveiling of the Jefferson Davis bust, held in the Capitol Building in Richmond, Virginia, on 25 June 1952. The bust was a gift of the state of Mississippi, and participants in the ceremony include Virginia Governor John S. Battle and historian Douglas Southall Freeman, who gives the keynote address on the life and legacy of Jefferson Davis.
  - Jefferson-Jackson Day, 28 February 1958, (WRVA-304); 1 compact disc. Duration: 57 min., 18 sec.
    This is a recording of the annual Democratic Party fund raising event, known as the Jefferson-Jackson Day Dinner, held at the Hotel John Marshall in Richmond, Virginia, on 28 February 1958. The recording begins with a brief part of a speech in which Harry Flood Byrd discusses his decision to run for re-election to the United States Senate. Byrd is followed by Governor J. Lindsay Almond's long introduction of the main speaker, Herman E. Talmadge, United States Senator from Georgia. The remainder of the recording is of Talmadge's speech, which focuses on praising Virginia's policy of Massive Resistance in response to the Supreme Court's decision of forced integration in the public schools, while criticizing the lack of government spending on the military. He rounds out his speech with criticism of the federal leaders for spending too much money on foreign aid, at the expense of domestic programs at home.
  - Jefferson-Jackson Day Dinner, [1968], (WRVA - 547); 1 compact disc. Duration: 44 min., 32 sec.
    Recording of the Jefferson-Jackson Day Dinner in the Grand Hall of the Hotel John Marshall. Watkins M. Abbitt, chairman of the Democratic State Central Committee and Fourth District Congressman, introduces the keynote speaker, Governor Mills E. Godwin, Jr. The bulk of the recording is Godwin's speech. Godwin praises the current Democrats of Virginia's congressional delegation, retired Senator A. Willis Robertson, retired Congressman Howard W. Smith, and the late Harry F. Byrd, Sr. He outlines the accomplishments of Byrd's gubernatorial term and criticizes the Republican Party's opposition to certain legislation. He fears the splitting of the Democratic Party into its divergent factions more than the power of the Republican Party. He calls for Democrats to make the party's diversity its strength. The first fifteen minutes of this recording is barely audible and primarily contains the voices of WRVA broadcasters preparing for the recording of Governor Godwin's speech.
  - Joan Brooks Show, August-September 1948, (WRVA - 67-68); Duration: 1 hr., 29 min., 16 sec.
    2 compact discs. This collection consists of three broadcasts of the Joan Brooks Show, a musical variety program, hosted by Sewell Brown and starring John Connelly, Wilson Angel, The Hospitality House Orchestra, and the hostess, "the girl with the voice you won't forget", Joan Brooks. Each program's musical performances were punctuated with witty banter between Joan Brooks and the other performers. The following is a sample of songs performed on the programs: "Funiculi, Funicula"; "It's Only a Paper Moon"; "Somewhere Beyond the Sea"; "Somewhere Over the Rainbow"; "I'm Nobody's Baby"; and "Every Day I Love You(Just a Little Bit More)."
  - Joe Morrissey's Summer of Discontentment, 1993, (WRVA - 486); 1 compact disc. Duration: 43 min., 20 sec.
    Recording of an entry by WRVA in the Virginia Association of Broadcasters awards competition for 1993, featuring segments on the controversy surrounding Joe Morrissey, Commonwealth's Attorney for the City of Richmond. Includes stories on the various investigations of Morrissey, his numerous suspensions from office, appeals, and reinstatements, his trial and acquittal on bribery and perjury charges, subsequent ethics violation hearing, and his campaign against opponent David Hicks.
  - Kemp's Konversations: Jamestown Visitors from England, 23 August 1957, (WRVA - 298); 1 compact disc. Duration: 29 min., 47 sec.
    This is a recording of the 145th weekly transcription of conversations between representatives of Virginia Business and Professional leaders and Verbon E. Kemp, Executive Director of Virginia State Chamber of Commerce. He is joined by members of the British Parliamentary delegation, who attended a ceremony commemorating the 338th anniversary of the first meeting of the Virginia House of Burgesses at Jamestown in 1619. They discuss the history of the British parliament, as well as variations in and details of British parliamentary procedures. They give impressions of Virginia and the Jamestown Festival. Kemp gives his impressions of post-war England, and his guests talk about their memories and tell stories of the bombings and changes since the war. They discuss the common heritage of Great Britain and the United States.
  - Kemp's Konversations with John S. Battle at Brussel's World Fair, 4 October 1958, (WRVA - 299); 1 compact disc. Duration: 25 min., 2 sec.
    This recording is of the 204th conversation between representatives of Virginia business and professional leaders and Verbon E. Kemp, Executive Director of the Virginia State Chamber of Commerce. The occasion is Virginia Day at the 1958 World Fair in Brussels, Belgium. He is joined by the Honorable John S. Battle, former governor and leader of the Virginia party at the World's Fair; Mrs. R. T. Pickett, member of the Roanoke City Council and official representative of the city of Roanoke at the World's Fair; and Mrs. Paul Watkins, editor and publisher of the Hanover County Herald Progress and official representative of the Virginia Press Association. The recording begins with the official Virginia Day ceremonies, held at the United States Pavilion on September 22, 1958, which is followed by a conversation the next day in the studios of the Voice of America, between Kemp and his guests, as they discuss their experiences on the trip over to Europe, their travels through Belgium's countryside, and their visit to the fair.
  - Kemp's Konversations: 6th Anniversary Show for WRVA's 35th Anniversary, 7 November 1960, (WRVA - 463); 1 compact disc. Duration: 25 min.
    This program is track 3 on WRVA - 463. On the occasion of WRVA's 35th Anniversary and the 6th Anniversary of Kemp's Konversations, Verbon Kemp, executive director of Virginia State Chamber of Commerce, leads a discussion with Sam Carey, program manager of WRVA-TV, Walter R. Bishop, WRVA public relations director, and John Tansey, WRVA general manager. They discuss WRVA's mobile broadcasting unit, Kemp's Konversations, WRVA's public service activities, the history of WRVA, and the establishment of radio in Virginia. This program is also available as track 1-2 WRVA - 464.
  - Kemp's Konversations: Discussion of Activities and Contributions of the PTA, 14 November 1960, (WRVA - 376); 1 compact disc. Duration: 23 min., 41 sec.
    Recording of the WRVA radio program, Kemp's Konversations, hosted by Verbon Kemp, executive director of the Virginia State Chamber of Commerce. In this program, Kemp leads a discussion with Mrs. Aaron Margolis of Santa Fe, New Mexico, of the National Congress of Parents and Teachers, Mrs. R. T. Atkinson, president of the Henrico County PTA, and Dr. Edgar Johnson, president of the Virginia Congress of Parents and Teachers. The group discusses the meeting of the Virginia Congress of Parents and Teachers recently held in Richmond and some of the activities of Parent-Teacher organizations.
  - Kennedy in Norfolk, 4 November 1960, (WRVA - 373); 1 compact disc. Duration: 20 min., 20 sec.
    Harry Saunders of WTAR Norfolk reports for WRVA on Senator John F. Kennedy's campaign speech at Granby High School in Norfolk. Also includes speeches by Governor J. Lindsay Almond and Congressman Porter Hardy. Almond introduces Kennedy and endorses the Kennedy-Johnson ticket for president. Kennedy criticizes Nixon's statement that the Democratic Party is no longer the party of Thomas Jefferson, Andrew Jackson, and Woodrow Wilson. Harry Saunders recaps the highlights of Kennedy's speech, and describes the crowd and their efforts to shake Kennedy's hand.
  - Kepone: A Portrait in Abuse, 31 December 1975, (WRVA - 428); 1 compact disc. Duration: 28 min., 44 sec.
    Recording of a documentary detailing the history of the manufacture of kepone (chlordecone), a highly toxic pesticide, by Life Science Products, a subsidiary of Allied Chemical Company, located in Hopewell, Virginia, and the subsequent illness of company employees and pollution of the James River. Includes details of the investigation of the company, interviews with employees, as well as local and state officials, company officials, and state legislators. There is also information on the closing of the James River to commercial fishing by Governor Mills E. Godwin.
  - Launching of the Submarine Robert E. Lee at Newport News, 18 December 1959, (WRVA - 237); 1 compact disc. Duration: 14 min., 38 sec.
    Highlights from the launching of the nuclear-powered ballistic missile submarine Robert E. Lee at the Newport News Shipbuilding and Dry Dock Company on 18 December 1959. Lon Backman describes the events, including the speakers, music, and the christening ceremonies. There is also an interview with Rear Admiral William F. Raborn, Jr. (1905-1990), director of the Navy's Polaris missile program.
  - Lee Naval Volunteers, 15 July 1942, (WRVA - 10); 1 compact disc. Duration: 15 min., 12 sec.
    Recording of a recruiting announcement for the Lee Naval Volunteers, United States Navy. Includes a skit concerning Jason Taylor and his desire to enlist in the Lee Naval Volunteers. While telling his parents of his intentions, Jason's father recounts the story of grandfather's involvement in the Virginia navy during the Civil War and in the battle between the Monitor and the Merrimac. Also includes a message from Ensign J. B. Johnson of the Richmond recruiting district calling for the men of Virginia to enlist in the Lee Naval Volunteer program, and a decree from Governor Colgate W. Darden dedicating July to the Lee Naval Volunteer program. Produced by WRVA Radio in cooperation with the United States Navy.
  - Legislative News, 19 February 1960, (WRVA - 371); 1 compact disc. Duration: 14 min., 38 sec.
    Harry Monroe, WRVA news broadcaster, reports on the 1960 Virginia General Assembly and the defeat of the sales tax proposal. Almond responds to the defeat of his sales tax measure. State Senator Harry F. Byrd, Jr., responds to Almond's attack on the opponents of the sales tax. Monroe also reports on legislation to permit the spending of county money to fund private educational institutions in Prince Edward County and news of sit down demonstrations at a downtown Hampton lunch counter by Hampton Institute students. Also includes the Capitol Squirrel commenting on the possibility of a new downtown convention center.
  - Legislative Roundup, January-March 1958, (WRVA - 313-320); 8 compacts discs. Duration: 7 hr., 12 min., 27 sec.
    The Legislative Roundup was a daily program covering highlights of the activities of both the Virginia House of Delegates and the Senate during the 1958 session of the General Assembly. Jack Clements hosted the program, with the assistance of Harry Monroe and Frank Wilson. Each program included a run-down of the day's activities provided by the radio announcers, which was interspersed with interviews and commentary from various delegates and senators. Examples of topics covered in some interviews include committee work and legislation involving everything from bills regarding quail season, disciplinary spanking in the classroom and minimum milk prices, to various attempts to either curb or enhance both Virginia's policy of Massive Resistance and Governor Almond's level of executive power in response to the threat of federal troops enforcing the integration of public schools in the Commonwealth.
  - Let's Go to Town, September 1944, (WRVA - 72); 1 compact disc. Duration: 30 min., 2 sec.
    This recording provides "A Radio View of Richmond, Virginia," as presented by the Armed Forces Radio Service to all the soldiers overseas and at home. Highlights of the program include a visit to the Westwood Supper Club to hear "Would You Like to Swing on a Star" performed by Pretty Kitty Breeze; Jack Kilpatrick, editor of the Servicemen's News, summarizes news from Richmond from the past year; and the Sunrise Hillbillies from WRNL and Sunshine Sue of WRVA perform "You Are My Sunshine" together. There is also a discussion regarding soldiers returning to civilian work, the Selective Service local board that will help them return to work, and a brief interview with a woman doing war work while her husband is away fighting.
  - Let's Ride Together: Virginia State Highway Advisory Committee. Program 1-2, 15 and 23 July 1942, (WRVA - 8); 1 compact disc. Duration: 31 min. 10 sec.
    Recording of two public service announcements from the Virginia State Highway Advisory Committee concerning the importance of car pooling to help save rubber and gas for the war effort. Program 1 includes a brief statement from Governor Colgate W. Darden, information on group riding clubs, a skit promoting group riding clubs and gas and rubber rationing, and music from Sunshine Sue (Mary Higdon Workman) and Her Rangers ("Nellie Bly"), Ramona Riggins ("Mockingbird"), Smoky Mountain Sweetheart Jane Allen ("Ole Chisholm Trail"), and The Rangers ("Ole' Dan Tucker"). Program 2 includes a statement from Major A. B. Curry of the Richmond Air Force Base on the importance of saving tires by riding together to help the air force and the uses of tires in the construction of the B-17, music from Burt Repine's Orchestra ("Melody in F") and Wilson Angel ("Columbia,Gem of the Ocean" and "Home on the Range"), and a skit promoting group riding clubs and gas and rubber rationing. Jack Stone of WRVA Radio produced both programs.
  - Let's Talk Business with Irby Hollans, 9 September 1960, (WRVA - 575); 1 compact disc. Duration: 5 min., 21 sec.
    This is a recording of an episode of "Let's Talk Business" hosted by Irby Hollans and sponsored by the Bank of Virginia, submitted for the 1960 UPI Awards. A nightly program that provided local updates on financial happenings in Richmond and Virginia businesses, this specific recording has information on Reynolds Metal, a meeting of Virginia Ford automotive dealers at the Mosque to preview the 1961 Ford models, a Federal Reserve Bank report that says Richmond department store sales are down from the previous year, an advertisement about the merger of Chesterfield Bank and the Bank of Virginia, railroad news from Virginia and around the country, and a calendar of events for various Virginia businesses and associations.
  - Let's Visit a Train Dispatcher, 23 September 1939, (WRVA - 5); 1 compact disc. Duration: 27 min., 56 sec.
    Program of a visit to a train dispatcher of the Richmond, Fredericksburg, and Potomac Railroad (RF&P). Broadcast from the east wing of the Broad Street Station in Richmond, Virginia. Includes highlights of the history of RF&P, demonstration of the work of a train dispatcher, detailed description of the job of a train dispatcher, the method by which passenger and freight locomotives are named, and a discussion of the number of train passengers who travel through the Broad Street Station on a typical day. The following employees of RF&P are interviewed: W. A. Aiken, Jr., General Superintendent of RF&P; J. C. Bullock, train dispatcher; J. E. Swift, Assistant to the General Superintendent; and Bernard L. Jones, trainmaster.
  - Linwood Holton Inauguration, 17 January 1970, (WRVA - 552); 1 compact disc. Duration: 44 min., 10 sec.
    WRVA reporters, Larry Dodd, Don Murray, and Joe Weeks, report on the inaugural ceremony for governor-elect Linwood Holton. The recording includes Andrew Pickens Miller, J. Sargeant Reynolds, and Linwood Holton taking the oaths of office for attorney-general, lieutenant governor, and governor, respectively, and the inaugural address of Linwood Holton. In his inaugural address, Holton emphasizes bi-partisanship and calls for Virginia to become a model for race relations. This recording also includes an WRVA's reporters providing an analysis of the inaugural address, Joe Weeks speaking with Mel Carico, political correspondent for the Roanoke Times, a description of the inaugural parade, speculation on the possibility of Senator Harry F. Byrd, Jr., becoming a Republican for his upcoming re-election campaign for the United States Senate, and music of the Queen's Guard Band of the College of William and Mary and the Robert E. Lee High School Band of Staunton, Virginia.
  - Little Oil Company Fire Coverage, 26 June 1975, (WRVA - 612-614); 1 compact disc. Duration: 2 hrs., 45 min.
    Coverage, 26 June 1975, of the fire at the Little Oil Company in downtown Richmond. The recording consists of WRVA's regularly scheduled programming, including "Open for Opinion" with Larry Dodd, and the "Tim Timberlake Show," but also includes updates on the fire. Alden Aaroe, Walt Williams, and Tim Timberlake report from the scene, with information on the fire and the leaks in two gasoline storage tanks, and the fear that it could spread to three tanks holding fuel oil and kerosene. Many of the updates concern the weather and traffic conditions. The fire was started by lightning the previous evening. A portion of Interstate 95 was closed due to the fire.
  - Lucy, C. T., History of WRVA, (WRVA - 548-550); 3 compact discs. Duration: 2 hr., 12 min., 9 sec.
    Recording of C. T. Lucy, former general manager of WRVA Radio, reading a history of WRVA Radio entitled, "WRVA Richmond, The Voice of Virginia, 'Down Where the South Begins.'" The history traces WRVA's history year by year from 1925 to 1968. It begins with Larus and Brother Company purchasing the largest broadcasting station Western Electric Company makes, and Pleasant Larus Reed, vice-president of Larus and Brother Company assigning Lucy to build and operate the station. It ends with WRVA moving into new offices and studios on Church Hill. A transcript of this broadcast is located in Box 30. This broadcast was recorded for Broadcast Pioneers in 1968.
  - Lucy, Calvin T., Interview, 2 November 1957, (WRVA - 119); 1 compact disc. Duration: 9 min.
    Interview, 2 November 1957, with Calvin T. Lucy (1891-1980), vice-president of Larus and Brother Company, conducted by Dick Gillis, on the occasion of WRVA's 32nd anniversary. Lucy, one of the founders of WRVA, discusses his early years with the radio station, and reminisces about the first night's broadcast and the individuals who were involved in it.
  - Lunch with the Girls, 6 March 1958, (WRVA - 561); 1 compact disc. Duration: 12 min., 50 sec.
    This program, hosted by Alden Aaroe, features short interviews and talk with members of the Richmond Association of Plumbing and Heating Contractors Women's Auxiliary while having lunch at a local Richmond restaurant. One member of the group discusses their work with Sheltering Arms Hospital. Aaroe also presents an orchid to one of the members, and the group participates in a commercial spot contest.
  - Lunch with the Girls, 17 April 1958, (WRVA - 561); 1 compact disc. Duration: 14 min., 5 sec.
    This program, hosted by Alden Aaroe, features short interviews and talk with members of an unidentified local patriotic and religious organization while having lunch at a Richmond restaurant. The members discuss the purpose of their organization and some of the fraternal benefits. Aaroe also presents an orchid to one of the members, and the group participates in a commercial spot contest.
  - Meeting on Proposed Merger of Richmond and Henrico County Sponsored by the Richmond Chamber of Commerce, 21 September 1961, (WRVA - 403-404); 2 compact discs. Duration: 51 min., 53 sec.
    Remarks, 21 September 1961, delivered by David J. Mays (1896-1971) and Garland M. Harwood, Jr. (1920-1973), at a meeting on the proposed merger of Richmond and Henrico County, sponsored by the Richmond Chamber of Commerce. Both discuss various issues and implications associated with the proposal, including the proportion of county vs. city voters, who would run the newly formed city if a consolidation took place, population growth in the city vs. the county, taxation and representation issues, court reorganization, and the extension of urban services.